Welcome back.
We're in our sublime text editor, and if you follow the instructions in the previous lesson, you would
have not only downloaded the text editor, you would have seen some of the basics as we typed code in
here.
This is our source code.
HTML source code.
And then we move across to our browser on the other side, where you can see that source code interpreted
and displayed in a browser page.
So what we want to look at now is just some of the basics around the tags and how the tagging work.
Now if you recall this is HTML.
So the most important tag or the first tag you've got to have is what.
That's right HTML.
So you just type h t and then you press tab.
The tab button.
And immediately it produces what we refer to as the skeleton.
So if you recall in our previous lesson we said this is our skeleton.
It's made up of these HTML tags HTML opening tag and HTML closing tag and various others.
So we're going to have a little look around some of these tags and briefly explain the tags that we've
got here.
And then we're going to look at some tags that allow you to do some basic formatting just so you get
a little feel for how this works.
Okay, to start with, as you know, we've got our head and we've got our body.
So the head generally all you put in there really is like, um, your title for your website, whatever.
If it's.
Yeah.
So you'll do something.
I mean, if you go and look at the moment, our website is all it's got is the title that's sitting
here inside the tab is what we called it, our web site, dot HTML.
That's not very exciting.
So if we go inside the actual title you'll see we can name that specific tab.
So like as you know, if you go on YouTube or Google, uh, you instantly know where it is because it
says whatever, YouTube or Google.
So now when we save this and we go back to refresh it, we see that cool website that I made.
Yeah.
So notice that's different.
You know, that's there is the actual HTML name, our website dot HTML.
But this here is the title, which is obviously far more useful.
It's also helpful.
This title for your search engines.
So when they start to search for things around what your website is called, this helps when it comes
to the search engine being easily able to identify you.
The other things that can go under head is typically metadata about your site.
Metadata means data about the data.
It's other things that can explain your site.
We're not going to look at it at the moment.
So at the moment all you're really interested in is title.
And that's the only thing that you've got to put inside this first part, which is head.
And so that brings us to the next part, which is now our body.
Okay.
So this is like we can name it to whatever and like or all the stuff we have inside.
Like we know pages that have lots of content and all of that kind of stuff.
Um, so, um, we'll go first through, like if we just said, um, uh, hello, we notice when we say
this, of course it's going to look beautiful.
It's gonna look very small and very uninteresting.
We can go over these different ones so we can go over each one.
Hit tab.
Okay.
So now what these are these are h1, h2 and h3 and etc...
We're gonna have a look at these are header types.
So it's basically saying okay I would like to put a piece of text and I want it to be header type one
okay.
So we can type.
Yeah.
So let's call it header one.
So you can actually see an example of what that looks like.
We'll just do one more.
So we'll do H2 for now.
Um hit tab tab okay.
Let's call this one header two.
So now we're going to see these are special tags that have been formatted and HTML recognizes them.
So immediately you see what's happened.
Header one is a large tag.
So you're getting a large heading.
And header two is a slightly smaller one okay.
So with HTML it goes all the way down to H6 which is.
Oh well let's give that one a try.
So h6 hit tab and let us type in header six and save it.
Go across to our browser refresh reloaded.
And then we got a little tiny little fella in there.
Okay, so more things that we've got um, beyond header is if we, uh, go here and we just tap in B
tab and that stands for brilliant I bet.
Okay.
So it's for bold bold bold if we want to make some text bold.
So if we just say this top bold so that.
Oh balls.
Balls, balls.
Be bold.
Be bald bald bald bald.
Be bald.
Here we go.
Okay, so, uh, we'll tap something next to it again.
Bold.
And we won't put this in any tags.
You'll just see the difference.
So we save that, um.
Refresh it.
We can see.
Okay.
So notice, uh, two things that are important.
If you've got very noticeable little eyes.
The first is you'll notice this one is in bold and that one is not in bold.
That is exactly how we said here.
This one sits inside of the tags B and close B.
This one does not, but you might have expected this to be on the next line.
Notice here it's not on the next line.
Okay.
Understand.
Remember and we mentioned this in an earlier session.
We'll show you how to put things on separate lines later.
But this is not a layout.
The fact that I could even stick another line in there, I could stick some spaces in front of that.
Save it.
Go across here.
What do you think it's going to look like when I hit refresh?
Come on, take a guess.
What do you think is going to look like?
I just changed it.
I moved it down another line.
I've moved it across.
Actually, I moved it right the way across.
So now it should actually come directly after that, but a few rows later.
Okay.
Save.
What's it going to look like?
Exactly the same.
Nothing changed.
Even though I saved it and refreshed it.
Because this is not a formatting space, it's not what I mentioned earlier.
It's not a Wysiwyg environment, so that makes absolutely no difference.
So all the formatting is done by the tags.
The tags are very important.
And in fact, if you want to just get an idea of how many, many, many tags there are.
If you press the opening bracket, it'll immediately bring up all the tags and the error loads and loads
and loads and loads of tags.
And so you can obviously choose.
And we were looking at the bold tag and you can see the different header tags.
I could choose it just like that.
So that's another way of doing it.
And it will choose a tag for you.
So there we've got like a header foreign save that.
Go back have a look and we've got header four okay.
So hopefully you've learned a lot about tags and the body and where you put all of this kind of stuff
and go explore.
Try it yourself.
Try go through lots of tags.
You'll notice many of them won't do anything unless you do something very specific.
So you can try, um, these tags H1B these are all directly change the text.
They um, they make your website look different.
So go play around, have some fun, see what you.
Yeah.
And also mess up.
This is how you're going to learn.
And we encourage we encourage making mistakes when you're doing stuff because, you know, we all make
mistakes and it's okay.
So I mean, maybe you're looking to do a bold tag or something and you and you do that and you say,
okay, this is going to be bold and you hit save.
And it's so exciting because that last thing is going to be in bold, and you happen to go across and
have a look.
And it isn't bold, but not for the reasons that you thought.
Because if you look carefully, you haven't closed the bold tag here.
And what's going to happen is that everything that comes thereafter is still going to be in bold, even
though you think it's finished now.
That's why it's very important to see that your tags open and close, and that tag there has not been
closed.
So it should have a closing A forward slash B and close.
And that is correct.
So have fun, mess around, do your thing.
Ultimately it's all about having fun, making mistakes.
Whatever.
Right?
Go do it.